this computer great thank you so much
Jason for making time to have a chat and
I like we met at the Commonwealth
Secretariat in October this year and and
I was just amazed by your long
trajectory both with with the
regenerative world but but also even
before that with the whole Green
Building world and Living Building
Challenge and Green Building Council and
all that so I would love to just hear a
little bit more about your trajectory
how you got into all this and
particularly the state of kind of the
regeneration rising in Australia where I
think you've been a key player of having
in the bridge to bring Ben and Bill and
Pamela to Australia so yeah I mean my
it's really rooted in my personal
journey and kind of formative teenage
years you know that what we experienced
is teenagers growing up in American high
schools but I came from a very I would
say conservative but in Republican
family
nothing sustainable nothing organic in
my life as a kid who lived in a kind of
a suburban community in Maryland
Columbia Maryland which was an
experimental plan unit development and
sixties by a guy named James brows which
was kind of cul-de-sac
you know 20th century poster child a
suburban sprawl and then my father got a
job in New York when I was 11 and we
moved to the suburbs of New Jersey which
is kind of so my I guess the geography
of where I grew up in two different
places from an adolescent teenage played
a pivotal role in my later year
development as a system I want to play
in particularly in high school I was you
know an interesting kid and it was very
curious about why I was calling myself
an AMA ologist which is a you know a
lover of everything music art science
you name it but I got into drugs and
alcohol pretty early so I was a very
drug-addicted teen
and I used to contract and contemplate a
process you know what I was experienced
in high school with my peers I remember
sitting around the room with that
understanding why are we all together
this group of boys or teenagers and and
why are we doing the things we're doing
and I remember they like pointing out
that every single one of us about twelve
of us in the room coming from the fourth
divorced parents I was like wow that's
an interesting pattern I want divorce
divorce divorce divorce divorce and then
oh where are the kids doing this stuff
like this this is like textbook to me
and I was trying to understand how two
young hadn't lived my life a bit I
haven't been worldly ever been out you
know traveling the world a bit so I just
didn't know what to do with that
you know what the patterns that I saw in
society what I've seen I didn't really
understand I you know went to college in
Colorado and that was my first time off
the East Coast and kind of a different
slower Way of life is more first time I
was surrounded by people that were
growing pot but I'll sift like organic
food I was exposed to this kind of more
green life when I lived in Colorado I
loved it all my friends we grow our own
food and been a lot of time in the
mountains hiking climbing so it's kind
of like is great for me and it's
transition I still care at my problem
with me and when I got out of school I
went back to New York City and you know
didn't really feel like I had purpose I
didn't feel like I knew what I wanted to
do I default was working in a
construction company to get you know
just to have a day job and pay the bills
I was a project manager at a
construction firm in New York I was
studying fashion design and evenings I
liked fashion and lived in Florence
Italy for a while during college but
really didn't feel like I had had lots
of ideas but never really just filled
any of him I felt kind of lost as young
as a young 20 year old something and um
I was still grappling with severe
addiction at that point and I write at
the end of college I had lost a fiance
I'm not kind of my high school
sweetheart was killing the carts in the
Mott and that kind of triggered a deeper
level of addiction and so this is one
1998 to 2000 and I you know really dark
two years for me very lost mentally
emotionally and didn't really feel
purpose in life and wound up checking
myself into rehab clinic and a lot of
dope Florida it was the winter after
2000 so it's January in 2000 had choice
of going to Minnesota or Florida
something I'll go to Florida I had to go
through medical detox and all this stuff
right it was my introduction to a and my
Ni and the 12 steps which is a really
important point I'll make later ties it
all back together and I didn't quite get
hold of that you know program we're at
the beginning but I have a sobriety date
of July 9th 2001 so I've been sober and
a 12-step you know person my life has
been reset at the age of 26 right and
when I got sober I discovered
architecture and I loved architecture
but I knew I sucked at it I was working
with an architecture firm for a summer
in 2001
after working in construction and just
to kind of learn the inner workings of
an architecture firm I plan to go back
to school of Columbia and the firm that
I work for worked in the South Tower of
the World Trade Center so I got my
sobriety - July 9th 2001 9/11 was about
62 days after that and I was in the
building that day I kind of escaped by
the skin of my teeth with my now current
and white he was both we worked in the
same room together or escaped together
but we were just friends at the time and
then the aftermath of that event I
noticed something about my resilience to
processing that terrorist event and what
I witnessed when I experienced because I
had this place this 12-step AAA program
I was able to discuss and talk about
that in a very healthy way
and I had peers looking after me in a
support system through the 12-step
program of a day that really helped me
navigate the post-traumatic stress
ignoring through that event different
than I saw my peers my peers who I
worked with we're all on medication and
in prescence post-traumatic stress had
kind of really took hold of them
mentally and I felt like I was
surrounded by zombies and workplace it
was so I saw the power of this program
that brings people together that have a
common identity of something or function
or something and how they work together
to heal themselves went away and I came
up with the idea of creating a 12-step
program
for the people that survived that day
including my beautiful wife is right
here we're gonna sue that interview and
we started meeting at sessions and cafes
after work and talking about this stuff
in a way that I would talk about it with
you like you know what we experienced
that day what we were feeling and we all
felt similarly you know what we were
feeling after the event and what we saw
the remember that what was doing to us
mentally
we were losing sleep at night if we had
fear being in the subway but that we
weren't alone in that and that that kind
of collective healing process was really
powerful for us and then those sessions
my wife and I fell in love so I kind of
talked about the journey with my wife
jennifer has kind of love from the ashes
now she has a background in architecture
design interior design architecture
preservation and while I was going home
being an architect she was kind of
pushing me to kind of be real estate
developer and so you should go into real
estate they make they I think it was
because she saw that they had more you
know power over how to make
transformation happen and I was reading
books about sustainability it was
reading books and all this stuff so this
is kind of the age my curiosity that I
had when I was 13 before I became an ADD
it became my name is now a new sober
don't like came back full force and I
kind of she gave me a book like James
Howard Kunstler probably geography of
nowhere the rise and decline of the
American
Manman landscape and that was like you
know ray talks about natural capitalism
being his sphere in the heart that led
to interface becoming a global
sustainability juggernaut that what was
my spear in the heart that really woke
me to the paradigm the Argus suburban
small I built invited Paragon and I grew
up in so it helped me and articulate the
patterns that I saw as a teenager and
led me on that trajectory that path
until I was 26 so I was able to
understand the spatial dynamics of
suburban sprawl the commute patterns of
father is the divorce rate you know the
lack of sidewalks and walkability the
behavior of teenagers in that society
but lack of having independence from the
home or place for us you know congregate
safely outside of the you know the
current world all these things came
rushing into me so it's kind of my
lightbulb moment where I was like oh my
god help me help me find my purpose and
the system that I want to change really
coming at built environment
transformation with social ecological
transformations respecting really my
sweet spot is how do I change social
dynamics a place so that you know our
life journey we are we're looked after I
do a teach my stage kind of thing so
then I started working for the the Death
Star's of developers so instead of going
to Columbia I went to NY you're gonna
masters a real estate finance and
development and that was like it really
because I was so weird because I wasn't
motivated on purpose I just devoured
books so I read the bibliography of Jane
counselor's book and read all those
books as I was reading and studying all
my textbooks in college so I had this
interesting dichotomy of like here's the
system a way of looking at investment
risks you know real estate investment
you know this stuff when I was like
walking in real ovens Hunter Lovins
Chris Alexander and I was complementing
these two things together and I was like
wow I gotta create I'm gonna bridge
these two worlds together
so for 20 years I've been kind of a
you know trying to be an architect to
change the kind of transition the
industry at scale towards the deeper
ideals around the watching social
conscious development so you know I was
the neophyte coming out of graduate
school working for the big developer in
Brooklyn fighting for the first LEED
certified buildings in New York you know
like can we just get indeed not even
sober just get it certified you know and
it was really interesting as it was um
there wasn't a lot of support systems
for change agents back then right there
just like I was a voice in like a notion
of you know sharks of developers trying
to convince people that just wanted to
make a lot of money to change the way
they looked at what they're doing as a
as a career and I got made fun of quite
a bit this is like 2003 2004 to LA to
think I'd lead certified 2002 and I was
like you know they may picked on me and
they called me like the green know
you're the green guy but then like 2005
was like a tipping point and all of a
sudden it was like hey remember he
mentioned I think the like he talked to
me about that can you can we look at
that again like all of a sudden it
became like a market driver had an
advantage
I was like how cool and that helped me
kind of elevate in my on my role but I
was also kind of looking to get out of
New York I've been there a long time and
grew up around there and we had a kid at
that point and he was really sick my
wife was still dealing with
post-traumatic stress 9/11 and we were
looking for me in a pasture somewhere
and it was like Austin Texas Portland
Oregon history out of Washington like I
want to be in a city that's kind of got
lower cost of living that's got the
music night food culture going on and it
was really between those cities but I
chose Seattle because it had friends
I've had some college there but I got a
really interesting opportunity to work
for Paul Allen's firm Vulcan Inc so Paul
was co-founder of Microsoft so that was
my kind of the beginnings of my journey
sure in New York where I really started
to create strive was in Seattle right so
I consciously said I want to be
in this city because I see like the
intellectual capital Kula sustainability
is beautiful here and I can just sponge
up all these incredible designers and
engineers and thinkers and Polish people
climate it so it's already eco cultural
place you know people are wearing
Patagonia they don't want to drive BMWs
because you're thinking to join BMW you
know it's this different kind of mindset
if you're not doing something
sustainable you don't really matter kind
of thing so the culture of the Northwest
is really powerful I just jumped in with
two feet and I and I got and I had a
really interesting sandbox of playing
with a billionaire you know who add not
only this massive real estate portfolio
but you know museums music venues sports
teams so there's all these different
avenues to look at change and I was a
project manager Union which is an
innovation district but I was kind of
pushing but it was so when I went from
kind of like you know still large urban
developments in New York I was dealing
with like this huge district now and the
scale of change and we can do around
energy water placemaking you know all
the different elements of a city and
I've been getting in the DNA of Seattle
to create a really dynamic place and
housing you know all the innovative
housing models so I spent like six years
there was really fruitful for me but a
lot of it had to do with spending time
with Jonathan Rhodes who is my mentor
and kind of like I put him up there with
Chris Alexander and few other people
that really profoundly influenced me in
the way I see the world perspectives
Jonathan's a developer in New York but
he's been the pioneer of so much
innovation in the world and just a
brilliant soul he was like I want to be
like him you know I'm just like follow
that dream and part of his work was
dealing with climate change and we have
founded an institute in upstate New York
even before I left for Seattle called
the garrison Institute and we had a
convening in 2005 about real estate in
the age of climate change which had a
lot of big important influential
developers around the country sit down
have this dialogue like okay
government's not really going to deal
with this we have an industry at the
store taking this on is the group that's
in this room yes we believe climate
change is real now we all start thinking
about how do we adapt our portfolios to
address climate resilience and change in
the change in climb in the future that
morphed into a initiative called climate
in mind the behavior in looking at the
neuroscience and behavioral dimensions
of climate change and being a you know a
little sponge in the room with all these
brilliant neurobiologist scientists
people like paul hawking were there
Janine Benyus would be part of those
events this was in like 2006 to 2009
2010 and I was just reading and learning
all this stuff and one of these was this
work by Columbia University called the
Center for research and environmental
decision-making and they have this
document they created called the
psychology of climate change
communication there's a very simple
accessible read but it got into thinking
about single action biases how when we
walk in tell the story create change we
have to speak to both hemispheres of the
brain so the you know the analytical
side but also the experiential side so
you have storytelling with data
storytelling with data and I started
using I was like well this is really
interesting I'm gonna start using this
as a way to do change agent work in my
company so what was always a really
really a lot of friction than doing
change agent working my companies I what
I started doing was getting people out
of the office and my this is my
technique that I learned that helped me
unlock a full great a lot of potential
around me I started taking people out of
the office into a coffee shop down the
street one on one and I would start by
making myself vulnerable right you
already heard me open up my story when I
started out you know drip a little bit
of my personal story into a conversation
sought to identify why this stuff's
important to me and kind of weave in
some data in storytelling and then that
person would make themselves vulnerable
and they start talking about their
connection to the issue
and I started to chelating a strategy
for how many you know men and then all
of a sudden after so many coffees there
was like 40 champions in the company in
all the different departments that were
taking on ownership repealing change
engine work in their department so it
kind of spread this kind of this model a
chain of the company that percolated up
after a number of years to completely
change the executive leadership in the
mission of the organization it was
really great and around the GSC happened
you know the global financial crisis I
just joined the board of cascading or
Building Council and we had a Living
Building Challenge put out there and we
hadn't started we hadn't founded the
International any teacher into 2010 but
2010 was a really pivotal year so the
two years leading up to 2010 2008 to
2010 I was tasked with looking at a
global change portfolio for Paul because
the global financial crisis opened up an
opportunity which slowed down our work
and realistic is that we were
constrained and I my boss got permission
to use motoric majority of my time we
look at world change stuff and all I
wanted to start with what Paul's passion
points were which were science sports
art and the other one science sports
arts
I can't remember the other one don't
forget it later but you had museums he
had cultural institutions on stuff so
right around the time we started they
didn't mention in future suit I had the
idea of where I looked across the street
from our office and we had the sports
dating when he owned the Seattle
Seahawks and opponent Romo is there's an
only sports day and I was like wow you
know like that's an interesting place to
play let me walk across the street and
see what those guys do too and I started
talking to them about sustainability
initiatives and technologies and things
that we can do to green the stadium up
and long story short we got a five
million dollar investment after a few
months of work to do massive energy
retrofit put the megawatt of solar
panels on top of the venue so as the
largest solar array in Washington State
but you follow that as a platform and
transition mindsets and the culture and
behavior of fans around sustainability
and what they can take action for in
their own home so we started sharing
that stuff with the Seattle Mariners and
other sports teams in the region and in
February 2010 I had the idea of
convening a dialogue around how do we
look at sports as a leverage point to
transition society towards
sustainability
so we hosted this first session of what
became the green sports Alliance which
is now a global nonprofit with every
major league sports team in North
America remember it's about a two
million dollar organization with six
people I sit on the executive committee
but it's been like it was an amazing
kind of pond the plan with the worth of
you an idea how do we bring this
conversation just to billions of sports
fans and how do we use iconic sports
figures like Messi and Ronaldo to
communicate sophisticated ways that kind
of shift society in a different
directory trajectory we're still working
on that platform and if it is
celebrating 10 years next year we have
our conference in Minnesota so that was
one really interesting kind of
trajectory and I started it with like
two other people wants another really
important person from a natural resource
Defense Council Allen Hershkowitz
I found
did the board shared it and I just
handed it over to my buddy Scott he's
one of the directors of the Mariners and
it's a really amazing being a
quintessential leader of sustainability
in sport and just kind of let it go you
know it's got to sit back on the board
but then let it grow the way it needed
to grow within that industry and the
same thing was happening with living
future Institute and we were kind of
really expanding our mission living
buildings around the world and there's a
lot of synergy with the growth that we
saw with Sports Center and today what
we're seeing what kind of communities
take home this deeper level of
understanding about sustainable
buildings and technologies so I mean
Seattle was a really amazing six years
from when I probably you know I got
offered to take on an even bigger role
but then I decided to come to Australia
challenge I'll trick it that decision
like I wanted to raise my kids out of
the u.s. you know I just feel like from
it from the age of ten I had this this
underlying frustration with America and
I'm like maybe I was anachronistic and
thinking America was great
maybe I'm an old soul I just saw
something in America that had lost its
way right it just sits and so the ego
the collective arrogance of America and
the ego of American and I humanizing at
the potential rise of America and it's
very insular it's very navel gazing yeah
and I didn't want I'm well I have been
you know great grateful grateful
grateful that I have the opportunities
to live overseas a bit when I was a
teenager when I was a troubled youth I
had teachers I got scholarships for me
and put me in Barcelona at first like
four months and it was like whoa I love
this like I love learning being a scene
and learning another culture and the
language to live and I became a kid I
became addicted to that okay I knew how
important it was to develop a level of
tolerance and more cultures and
countries and live in and kind of really
develop a more worldly view and it will
be mine
so it was really important
my kids were raised a different
different one I think it was so
important like I I've been to 35
countries on five continents by the time
I was 29 I was also a little bit
addicted to kind of seeing new places
and new cultures and it shapes you in
but it also makes you understanding that
and there are different ways of being in
different ways of seeing the world and
it doesn't take that much more than when
you've seen that to understand that you
just your perspective can only be
limited because there's so many others
and I thought oh the other and that's
that's like Mary can just get that yeah
there's so many great things about
American American has so many different
personalities a book at six Americas
it's really good but I just you know I
wanted them and I'm lucky that I have a
wonderful wonderful partner in my wife
Jennifer but it was you got the same
adventurous soul is an idea it's like
you know we I took an opportunity and a
gamble to come down here and work for an
international development organization
where I saw you know I felt I felt
suffocated in Seattle where I work
didn't want to do anything outside of
Seattle I saw all these other poverty
things happening across the world I
won't play into there and there and
there and the idea was that if I worked
for a global company I could take what I
was doing in Seattle expand it
internationally that wasn't the case
though I'm very tough doing it in a
corporate shareholder own organization
but six years I've been here I've not
been on the same trajectory that I had
in Seattle the impact I had with the
government and climate movement white
house stuff we were doing on climate
change policy it just didn't couldn't
connect with the company that was you
know I was kind of stuck in this little
role but what grounds me and it's it's
it's somewhat frustrating when I moved
down here I felt like I stepped back 10
years instant in time with regards to
sustainability but the stuff they're
thinking through now there's stuff that
we did in the early 2000s or late 2010
with policy around climate resilience
adaptation
energy efficiency all this stuff that's
that's still taking hold now here and
probably thirty years ago a lot the
other thing I do is work on social
equity in students and housing issues
were coming thirty years behind in that
regard but regardless of the frustration
I have from an industry perspective when
I do here my practice here why I'm super
grounded here is because of the First
Nations perspective so they have
original a lot of my thinking even when
I was a teenager and listened positively
in New York was influenced by a lot of
firstnet being I was very drawn the
First Nation culture and ideology and
you know let's express the movies
everything else but there was something
deeper than I was always trying to chase
even when I was trying to engage her
trying to North West and I saw how
regenerative development was so heavily
influenced by that and Bill Reid from
agenesis became a really good mentor for
me in like 2008 so I've been you know
bouncing things off him and working with
him for a long time and book sharing a
sharing knowledge and it's always kind
of like oh that's interesting
and Carol Sanford who runs that
regenerative business world she live
down the street from me in Seattle it's
use who I work with a bit on the on the
bulk and stuff you know these are all
the people that were influencing plenty
Fisk in Austin Texas and she happens
Paul and Amy you know what I read their
books I want to meet them and become
part of the world and just you know and
we respectfully be a next generation
custodian of their work they like a
carrot or David Suzuki you know when we
had the living futures it was great
because we could host all these people
you know it would bring all those
amazing user in the world we found that
the setting up of the living futures
Institute sponsorship make anita fund
summit foundation JPB foundation we had
really good initiatives that were
responsible I helped raise a lot of
money when I was there on the board
we had membership so we had an operating
budget of like four million bucks
so from revenue from a number of
different things Living Building
Challenge was a big one and the living
in future unconference was a big revenue
generator so that was it was a good and
I didn't go a lot over Jake Jason and I
still work together so it's a great
family practitioners a kind of came out
of that that generation two from 2008 to
2015 and continues so the work I'm doing
now and kind of expanding the field
there's a lot of credit goes to Carolyn
Robinson who you saw in the video when
we were in London right she's this
amazing person so she connected to with
Genesis and brought it into Auckland and
for five years it's going to really been
taking hold of creating a nodal
transformation centre in Auckland New
Zealand which is really powerful
platform not just for them but for
Pamela and Bill and Ben and ulama
Genesis because of the Maori influence
and how things go in doing so when you
do new retreat and training there on
Mirai you're with the Maori you're
learning Maori ideology language it's a
very interesting cultural emergent
process that happens and when they all
knew I need bill and was bringing bill
down their talks and engaged me and like
we all just connect it up a world
there's a really great there's probably
a hundred and fifty people that have
gone through training now in the last
five years in Australia New Zealand and
we're like a family of practitioners but
we're this is what Dom would be
interested in to talk to you in the car
right now what I see is that they go
through this kind of mental model
training with their Genesis for that
kind of three-month training and then
they kind of get dropped off they're
like what do I do now so this what I've
had to do in my career my trajectory is
take the ideals of a better development
and figure out how to apply them through
a broken system right the banking system
the finance just an evaluation system
the project management of it like how to
actually make a living building work at
scale
and that led me in a lot of different
directions but you know I have a
delivery framework that I've had to
cultivate over the last ten years on how
to manage and deliver regenerative
developments for reduce risk costs added
value sell it get it to the planning
approval process all that stuff so we're
looking at doing a training sessions now
to help practitioners here particularly
ones that have signed up for the
architect's declare movement to really
further their skill sets and
understanding the role and how to manage
and execute on this stuff it's one thing
to understand of what it's really the
house that we're missing and moving here
in the industry but I'm not doing that
with just my perspective my business
part is Aboriginal as I'm always the
curious learner entomologist as you
heard me start my conversation I've
learned more in the last three years for
my Aboriginal brothers and sisters and I
have in the previous you know 17 years
of my journey
I'm also understanding uniquely the way
that Westerners have kind of colonized
First Nations practices around the world
called it something else and use it for
their own financial benefit like Ophelia
or like permaculture you know things
that we use in our world I was blind to
the fact where that where those
practices were influenced by Tomas and
seeing how Aboriginal people had mosaic
fire regimes and how they manage their
food and agriculture in the complex
system of society and management
essential and so what I'm doing Network
starting in my business partners chell's
Marshall and chels I my wife knows I'm
like super passionate about First
Nations culture and ancient
civilizations with that so Charles was
doing a talk at the Australian is in
maybe three years ago and I said oh my
god that's the person I need well the
same people I was trying to chase in the
US and she was like
connection to that world and I needed
and I you know stalked her a bit at the
talk and we had a conversation got a
copy I invited her in to a project and
we were having a coffee in Canberra and
she didn't know who I was already but
but the way that you and I have
cultivated our minds from living around
the world and absorbing this this way of
thinking about the world from her
generative perspective I was able to
connect with there was a white person
more than anyone else has to pass and
she cried in my arms for like that we
cried because I saw how this really
powerful moment they may have been like
best friends for like three years like
I'm mentoring or her am agender
development she's been mentoring me in
Aboriginal knowledge but you know I have
to earn the right to accrue that
knowledge and in that world so after two
years now I'm invited up now to meet the
elders and see different parts of
country and learn different practices
and knowledge and she's always helping
me understand how what she's learned
from her ancestors and her parents and
how she was raised aligns with biophilia
and biomimicry and regenerative practice
and we call it that because that's the
Western construct that we had to create
so we've developed this platform called
cultural reciprocity right so it merges
my journey with her journey and the
knowledge fusion of Western science
Aboriginal knowledge systems and
traditional practices an advanced
community making so we're trying to
build bridge between cultures and we
over the summer we're planning to start
a school called the gun banger school
for life center design so she's a Kim
banger nation she's like a banging woman
and her background is you know super
intact knowledge transfer from her
lineage going back thousands of years
for totem is this is a see her people
show them as the ocean so they're very
marine focused so she's a systems
ecologist and a marine biologist and an
Aboriginal ecologist so she is a perfect
blend of these different worldviews so
she's got the storytelling and the
science
the data is really horrible they like I
had this moment and what you're just
sharing is really touching me because I
think one of the most beautiful moments
for me this year has been on the last
day of the meeting where we met in the
Commonwealth Secretariat
and back at the hotel I somehow got into
a conversation with Johnny Freelander
from from New Zealand and and we had
this brief mind melt where where we had
this open like I had this opportunity to
just test out some of the key frameworks
that inform my way of thinking in my my
practice and then he would immediately
sort of pick it up and say yes in our
people understand this in the dislike
but like he would create the mirror
piece of what my Western mind framework
in terms of scale inking design and
nested wholeness and and and
interconnectedness or or this this hunch
that there's something wrong with our
understanding of time that that the past
the future and the present I actually
co-present and that the only place where
you can ever do anything is in the
moment now but it is connected in both
ways to the past and the future and that
that we re patterning the future in the
present and so I would come up with
these frame like share these frameworks
with him and then he would mirror them
back to me from deep Maori knowledge and
and I never felt so corroborated
something like probably in a limited
understanding but that I would East was
some half of understanding so I'm amazed
with how decolonizing our minds right so
there's this process of unlearning made
we were educating and grew up in a
Western context and ideology
epistemology that at 44 years old
I'm unlearning more in the last few
years and I have in my previous it's
like it's amazing and it's just it's a
very powerful platform though if over
the summer which
to create this online school around life
center design that few Jesus indigenous
knowledge and Western thinking but it
would be pairing up like you with Johnny
and having a non online you know an hour
discussion between how you talk about
this and you know I'm a giant on our
perspective and then tapping into the
marine side of that but William the
food's just a whole different way to
tell the story with two different
worldviews tell it then that's such an
important but I mean he said earlier
that you were a bridge builder and back
in that world can the green world in the
construction world and but this bridge
building off of deep-rooted indigenous
knowledge into the the Western world in
a in a meeting each other at a height or
even in even getting arrogant Westerners
to connect with humility to a point to
understand that what we've lost in our
obsession with technology and science
and the kind of where systems thinking
as Johnny calls it we we disconnected
with the knowledge of how to live in
place over ten thousand years in a way
that we are godless that we are keystone
species that help that place flourish
and unfold its potential as part of that
place and we call that wisdom primitive
and so what I'm hearing that what you
what you're building I think probably
the most important bridge that we need
to build to reconnect a great but
actually made us survive for ten
thousands of years as a species
literally
80,000 here and the other thing is that
so great is this the longest hand
continental peace period of any race of
humanity in history well the complexity
of that society and how the advance we
saw only primitive with our Western eyes
when we came here whoever came a bit
yeah there's a girl in here in the tip
of the iceberg and DOM is rooted and
written this side up
just by the way we're recording this
there's a little bit of an echo with
your with your computer say something
again sorry sorry I was like I might
turn off my video delay is that better
when I first lived in Australia bill
introduced Vietnam Saddam's been a
friend and kind of she's really been one
of the pioneer it's really created a
fertile ground for regenerative even
discussion around in the vernacular in
the industry here then doing that as an
academic as a practitioner and has a
really exciting role so Tom's been a
force of change down here and both New
Zealand and chiozza with me as well but
it's really nice to meet you and Dom at
we've we've only been in contact by
email a couple of times so like Jason
and I just dove into this as a little
interview that I'm hoping to share as a
blog and so I hope you're okay with that
and that's great maybe maybe now that
you joined us I'll give you give you
brief opportunity to share a little bit
how you have been working with
regeneration in Australia and and help
to kind of what Jason just said helped
to kind of create the foundations for
Australia New Zealand seems seem to be
the hub of regeneration at the moment on
the planet yeah so I just want to
actually respond to your previous
conversation so I've been listening in
for about 10 minutes I was trying to get
my technology going this um as Jason
knows I've been working on this idea of
modern custodianship which isn't just
about respecting their past knowledge
you know their past knowledge which is
still current so it's difficult one
perspective
their knowledge but to also say well
when that knowledge is applied to
current issues here is the innovation
that is occurring so Jason and I have
got a colleague who's looking at
artificial intelligence so what if we
designed the algorithm into the bangle
area in a indigenous circular expense
what was the difference
how would the world look differently and
and so there's some really interesting
stuff in that yes and conversation
between indigenous wisdom and knowledge
and thinking and being and the current
issues and thinking and being and it's
not about religion either it's actually
about coming together and seeing what
emerges so that sort of I'm really
interested in supporting however that
emerges in the world as for my role in
regenerative development in this part of
the world I see myself as mycelium so
something that's become more and more
apparent to me is that I'm not really a
front person what I like to do is
connect people pass on messages hear
what people are saying see their
potential and then connect them into
system where that potential can
contribute
I think Jason you know you've seen me
work and I think that's where I'm at my
best and and so you know Daniel that's
why you know we're seeing everything
happening out of Europe I want to make
sure you were connected into it and I'm
glad that you were but it's that that's
kind of my space I remember mycelium
maybe of the regenerative development
network or I will it seems to have
really really grown a lot stronger and
and so it gained its own momentum which
is wonderful and and have you managed
both in Australia New Zealand to
cultivate ongoing connections between
the people who have gone through the
regenerative practitioner training and
and have that shared background in those
shared frameworks or
after the course of people just go on
and try to work on how to make those
frameworks actually work in their daily
practice alone but yeah so there's a
bunch of us that are all still connected
and support each other there are a bunch
of people that have added it to their
food they are in the world so for me the
the TRP the Regenesis work came together
with the Colorado lenses works came
together with my placemaking work came
together with you know they're just
trying to build capacity in the world be
contributed but all of those things came
together and so it isn't about purity to
one idea it's about taking from that
what supports me in my practice and
makes me feel like I'm contributing but
I would say Jason and you might be able
to add to this as well that we're mostly
all connected in as much as we can be
but then also you know Jason's doing
amazing work with chills and and working
at that big end of town and actually
cutting through because of his wonderful
accent and experience in America people
said happen listen I wish I hadn't have
lost my are you so your original that
Dominic I didn't know that yes yes yes
I'm Dutch but I grew up in Brazil and
South Africa so I have another we were
talking earlier about how important it
actually is to have experience lived
experience of different cultural
contexts yet again the corroboration of
that indeed indeed
and I think the other critical thing is
to have that last moment where it's like
the initiation ceremony of building from
our child into an adult where you
realize that you you make a choice you
know you make a choice to become a
contributing part of the system I mean
that's another really important aspect I
think he's speaking to something that
because Jason also shared his personal
story earlier that this the fact that
the world is in such a mess is partially
to do with the fact that we are being
governed by uninitiated teenagers no
matter what age they are and and and
that's really one of the big connections
to First Nations or indigenous cultures
is that that moment in life where as a
teenager you invited into a capacity it
makes you cross that threshold into
mature membership in your community and
of course understanding community not
just as the human community but the
wider community of life that that's
really what's so fundamentally missing
in our culture and what I feel
it just is that that the current climate
crisis and the unraveling of ecosystems
that the cascading ecosystems collapse
around the world is somehow creating
conditions that at species level and
that are similar to a rite of passage
because it is making us face death at
the higher level and that is making us
reflect on why are we here what's why is
this worth it and what is our role and
who are we obliged to all the questions
that rite of passage rituals kind of yep
parking people and in my big hope and
actually my only hope is that we will
get that shift of personal development
consciousness shift through this crisis
and and mature quickly actually become
healers and and avoid civilizational
collapse that now so many people are
speaking about and at the same time also
gain the maturity in that process that
we aren't quite and so going on anymore
because I think that's a part of it to
be able to let go to your own like like
to embrace your own mortality and that
things are fine a finite and then live
from from a place that that is actually
about really connecting in the moment
and and caring for the relationship that
we can have while were here so and jump
in anytime
um have you spoken to Charles Eisenstein
well I have no chance for for a few
years but I we've never really had very
deep one-on-one conversations yes
because this this this discussion around
you know the maturation process and the
initiation ceremony and the permission
to become an adult and contribute as an
adult it's very much around his thinking
that comes from that because we have a
shared mentor and he he's very closely
linked with Gigi Coyle and from the
school of lost borders in in California
and and that's where I got that deeper
understanding from having done my Vision
Quest with them and Gigi and has been
mentoring Charles a lot Charles the one
thing that I have a bit of a pipes for
Charles about this that he mm doesn't
honor lineage very much in terms of his
communications I think like I think he
believes that ideas come out of the
collective consciousness so there
everyone's fine I can I can underwrite
that but at the same time um naming your
mentors are naming your elders and
naming your sources helps other people
to find those streams up to travel
upstream and that and in an honest and a
donor's they get to you as a learning um
yeah so that was my first source
my second thought is that I don't
necessarily believe that our First
Nations people had it completely right
because they were still fragile right
wake time mean and and disrupt to this
system so
it's it's as much for them to learn us
for us to learn and then move together
is really how I how I see things
yes they had connection to place yes
they had those initiations theremin s I
had respect they were part of as you
said the garden and tending the future
but they were still fragile and and
particularly within the number of people
in the world at the moment we need to
find a different solution or in a
different way together that uses that
past wisdom current knowledge and our
current situation and context to move
forward and so that's why I talk about
it you know it's it's not about
privilege in either system you know
there's Eastern Western and indigenous
so there's there's lots of different
ways but it's about yes and conversation
and then difficult because there is so
much history the framing that I like a
lot I like with regard to this is I
don't know if you've ever come across
the small little book by own Barfield
cults em saving appearances and in that
book he makes the point that like he
speaks of original participation and
then the separation of the Enlightenment
and the kind of disappearing into our
mind and Science and Technology and then
he speaks the final participation as the
coming together of those those two so it
is a movement forward and that recovers
the wisdom of the past but but he
combines it with with the wisdom of
science and technology as well so I I
think did you mention that that book and
author again and oh in Barfield saving
appearances he's he was not the
university scholar who has been very
influential in the anthroposophical
world is kind of part of that well but I
would just just briefly going back to
something you said earlier with a I am
and bringing indigenous ways of thinking
together with those kind of technologies
I I do sometimes wonder whether part of
the
the wisdom of indigenous cultures is to
also choose wisely what technologies are
actually worth using like like I feel
like we have a tendency to use
technology because we can like somebody
comes up with oh we could create this
technology and then somebody I saw we
could use it for that and and mainly
most of our technologies have really
been developed within a context of
trying to kill each other and the
military development complex but I am
concerned that we we end up using
technology too much and like the kind of
bits and bytes type of technology
instead of coming back to the social
technologies that the that we could live
a much richer and more meaningful life
with with with less technology in our
lives what do you think about yeah I'm a
big fan of less technology I was on a
panel with for the World Wildlife
Foundation few months ago and I was with
me and like Schneider Electric and all
these digital people they're looking at
smart homes of the future and how
technology is going to make our lives so
much better
I was the diversion voice on the panel
like my kids are on their phone all the
time we're trying to deal with new like
parental management technique so it's a
new age for parenting kids that in
technology age what does it mean to
their social skills if they're
everything's on here so there is that
needs to be a cautious waving before
with the application and adopting a
technology you know Nicole and I'm a big
fan of like no phone holidays you know
like you know getting back to basics and
face to face contact and new things and
well the way usually was platform right
now I can't engage face to face but I've
also since I've been indoctrinated to
your original culture here with my
brothers and sisters it's my
understanding of technology has changed
of thinking about technologies I was
developed by them thirty thousand years
ago and
we have a very contemporary wake you
like this with the issues we're having
with the bushfires writin we had when
you had Aboriginal occupation of the
country the majority of nations use a
seven season calendar and they had a
national scale fire you know stick
regime of managing the landscape not
only for prevention of out of control
fires from lightning other sources but
also stewardship of life and species and
plants and undergrowth and understory
and food for the mammals and other you
know things so they they did these cool
mosaic burn strategy and everyone
participated it by keeping everything
below a meter silicate to be on the
ground and they did it in a way they
knew where the animals will be able to
move safely out of the way fire and
never be a danger and that at a national
scale and it also did the cultivation
with allowing the ashes you know let the
steeds pop for the two tumors though
there are tubers and they were growing
so it has brilliant brilliant stuff and
Western I think some Western I think
some contemporary Australian like we're
all flat surface try to adopt some of
that self but we wouldn't be if we have
that learnings and culture reciprocity
of using an original approach doing it
with Western Approaches we probably
wouldn't be in the situation right so
when I call that I was a trek Balin
Council down in South New South Wales on
Monday who were you know very strong
Aboriginal Land Council on their own
land have their own governance there
almost there one of like the for
precedent councils and have a
sovereignty in the Commonwealth
but the real a couple others and I
called him up and say how you doing with
the fires like go ahead we we need our
Barrett Burns two years ago which really
fine they because of the seven secret
seven season cycle they knew how to
manage this and there was a politics of
fire regimes with different nations of
clans was really managed and we come
down and copy-paste at a four seasons
calendar around food growth landmass all
those things and you see the report not
so we copy and paste of their all of
season calendar but it's of courses and
calendar based on something arbitrary
you know and not the moon of arbitrary
so much but you know wearing a look at
times within nature so you know some
years summer might be shorter and some
years Samoa might be longer it depends
and when a certain thing happens in that
environment that switches the season not
a date and I think that's the great
wisdom of it in that it's a set of rules
that allows you to act in response to
what's happening in a place in response
to the climate yeah I remember in 2000
yes and when was it 2009 I helped to
bring pioneers to Europe and to
conferences one in in Zeist in Holland
and one in New Zealand and in infant
hall and I had the opportunity to meet a
guy called Dennis Martinez and was part
of the First Nations in in the u.s. who
work a lot with traditional ecological
knowledge of indigenous American tribes
and their fire regime in California
really kept the like it's yet it's
another example of not following the
fire regime practices of First Nations
people in California's has created the
conditions about from bad upkeep of
electrical lines by the power companies
to create the fires in in California
it's yeah we how do we now that we are
approaching 8 billion people on the
planet how do we value those cultural
inputs and then square it up with the
fact that there's a lot more people with
us like on the planet now and we have a
much more brittle system because we've
degraded ecosystems all over the place
drastically
well I I think it's partly the the and
and moving together conversation it is
some sort of technological input as well
but it is as you said that wise choosing
of their technologies and I don't
necessarily think that the degradation
that we've created is irreversible I
think it's a mind shift and that's what
regenerative development is all about if
we you know put on put on our big girl
and big boy pants and and say what can I
do now all eight billion of us turn
around say what can I do to support a
thriving place things will change very
quickly and it and it's creating those
narratives and those examples and that
understanding I'll just thank you
someone say I've done four major
building projects over the last three
years twenty years ago I have to fight
to get a water painting framework thank
you today we're talking about you know
they're discussing the merits of the
Living Building Challenge and how it's
not pushing them hard enough and and you
know they see the multi-million dollar
huge organizations who now had the
language of Biophilia biomimicry
connection contribution bringing in
social enterprise all these lots of
things so there is a consciousness
emerging and Chrisman de Plaisance talks
about you know the innovation curve and
there's at some point that innovation
curve keeps on except from the early
adopters into mainstream and that we're
actually getting quite close to that
within the concepts of and and it is it
is the people holding on very fiercely
to old ways that is stopping the full
emergence of this but I'm actually quite
hopeful around our ability to actually
contribute to future thriving yes our
population number is a huge issue but
you know somebody said you know you've
got to have it you've got to have a
stand on population I've got a friend
with five kids and the 15 is going to be
the kid that changes
we'll just like Beethoven was all that
Mozart was the ninth kid of a shady lady
then you know turn the world of the
world of music around it's very
difficult to make rules around these
sorts of things yeah about a narrative
that people carry with them no I have a
concern actually about because I hear a
lot of people coming back to the
overpopulation issue and and I actually
think that it's a dangerous mean in the
sense that yes over time over a century
it will probably be wise to slow to
bring populations numbers down and but I
think that that's a natural process like
we already have the data that shows us
as soon as you educate women the the
number of kids and families do naturally
go down all over the world and and that
most most likely M the human population
will start dipping in the second half of
the century even if we this this got
horrible catastrophes but but I think
that there's a sort of right wing
conversation happening at the moment
that that is almost preparing people for
justifying some kind of larger was to
reduce population numbers that is really
dangerous and I completely agree with
you we have the potential to become
healers in place for all of us and then
it's actually a benefit that there's
that many of us and and we we can create
shared abundance for all of humanity and
that for me that's that's a good point
because like when I hear it's on one
it's wonderful to be working with these
large real estate developers and but but
to what extent are we still like so many
of the drivers of our current economic
and monetary system are degenerative
it's structurally driving people to
compete with each other and an exploit
nature
and when we have absolutely absolutely
I'm not saying that it's the right model
under seeing I'm seeing a shifting
conversation at all level yeah the
patterns are moving in the right
direction for me like I look past the
Trump's and the Boris's the other
neoliberalism movements what happened
here that's just kind of blips it is
those with power grass of desperation to
hold on to that without a fearful change
I see the reaction and the consciousness
shifting happening in a response to that
you have this democratic socialist
movement on the rise across the UK and
across the u.s. empowerment to you know
less advantaged citizen groups happening
all this movement that's Blessed unrest
the politic all value is going book is
really galvanized the global movement
the climate activism of the next
generation Retta I mean that new
dimension at scale across the world is
this global shift of human consciousness
but we have to we have to protect them
as one of the things I'm worried about
this whole young movement around climate
change isn't supported with the
regenerative narrative of you know just
just like Pamela Megan and those guys
say you might see potential at a hundred
and it might come out of twenty it's
still much better than if you hadn't
been involved but often these the
idealism of young and wanting to make a
difference means that they get burnt out
because I can't see the impact of the
little things that might end up being a
nobody in 10 years time may turn into it
yes and it really worries me that we're
not supporting these movements with some
of that you know thinking that we have
all been working on I think that's the
big challenge for the next like in terms
of the urgency of the fierce urgency of
now with climate change now like it's
really the challenge of the next year or
two to make that connection of this like
2019 was the year of Greater and
extinction rebellion and waking
a whole like massively larger percentage
of the global population up to the
urgency to act on climate change but it
has been a message of I want you to
panic extinction is near that kind of
yeah
urgency driven and and what on the one
hand that's activating to some extent
but it is also like if we don't connect
that and particularly the young people
of riders for future movement to the
deeper practices that some pioneers that
Jason and I were mentioning earlier like
like Amory Lovins and Paul Hawkins or my
mentor John Todd word did my PhD with
and David David all and permaculture
movement and and Mollison and all these
guys they are we know a lot of ways how
to heal landscapes and and what if the
discourse of Greta would shift towards
regeneration as possible we can heal the
planet and we actually know how to and
then to bring all these young people
into new types of education systems that
because our universities are desperately
seletun the way that they and basically
like I was just talking to somebody
yesterday about this this need donor
Macy's framing of that we need to be
hospice workers to an old system and
midwives to a new and right now all
these woman's just look at what's dying
and the old system but we're not having
enough people in the streets talking for
that future of us being healers of the
planet again and in that process healing
ourselves and so I think that's that's a
key shift that we have to make in the
next 24 months what I've been trying to
do since 2009 create those alternate
narratives that show us the the way
after the disruption yeah yeah we was
getting this dialogue with
without Gore in the early days of the
climate reality project because it was
very you would do his presentation but
it was very dystopian something like cat
o'clock you know cataclysmic future and
it was we're talking about the whole
bucket
you gotta find the opportunity the
opportunistic future and where's the
hope in that message yeah that show we
are on the ground work that's happening
and carrying the hope maybe have you
both connected to this project that has
just got launched last week calm down
have you heard of it Mountain is a
partnership between future stewards Ted
and YouTube and it's it's a process that
is trying to basically drive on a making
um it's the process to drive very the
turn towards basically zero emissions by
2050 across all sectors using getting to
mainstream through channels like Ted and
and YouTube and but really focusing on
solutions focusing on what we can do and
I think it'd be really interesting to
connect both of you into that that that
world and the beginning because Jason
mentioned Al Gore ago at the launch of
countdown mentioned that system
psychologists quote that things always
take longer than you think but then they
also happen much faster than you ever
thought they would be possible and I
think we're just at that point where it
feels frustrating for people like us
who've been working on this for 20 years
and how little has shifted and some of
our mentors have been working on it for
40 years but I think we're at the cusp
of seeing rapid shift happening but it
is connecting solutions to the people
were now on the barricade saying we need
to act
so III need to go to bed and all of that
sort of thing what to make well it was
wonderful to just have this opportunity
to to connect me we'll do it some other
time to explore beyond pond yeah so I'll
just send you an email and wrap up with
Jason just now and and then we'll we'll
see when we have a conversation maybe in
it does January look good for you for
another conversation towards the end of
January great yep we're on holidays I
think to the 25th oh yeah wonderful
really nice to see you thanks for
showing up even if it was late but it's
just nice to make that first connection
I feel like I know you but actually
thank you Jason
you owe me a coffee and I am and I blues
jazz nice well that's good we do well
coming down a teacher regenerative
practice like a development course from
GBC a and thank you alright so I'll let
you know down that yeah okay yeah come
interesting interlude in our
yeah you do pick up on live there's like
complementary skill sets needed it's the
collective intelligence or network
performance it's really important and
shaping this movement it can't be one
person's view like DOM and I weren't
really together she has this very
academic way of coming in and I had a
practitioner way and got a couple
clients together we work with fuse those
together they what's we know what what's
you experience because one thing that
I'm I'm sort of having been in the kind
of intentional community eco village
movement like I've spent good time
sitting in circles trying to make
consensus
decisions and getting everybody's voice
heard and and I know how slow that can
also be and luckily the the new more
agile methods like socio cracy and make
that process a lot easier but I still
looking at things like what's happening
in the every time on the globe now where
there is some form of public vote to a
large group of people voting on an issue
the surprise seems to be that people
vote the wrong way like thought vote
wards for the demagogue vote for the
people who are playing the media and
misinforming them and end up like I mean
what just happened in the in the UK is
another example of like clear analysis
that labour didn't lie once in any of
their campaign slogans and that the
Conservatives were 80% of them were
misleading but but it seems to be
successful what I'm trying to get at is
having had an education system that
alienated us from each other and from
the natural world for so long and having
been manipulated by mass media into
being busy consumers and wanting things
that are really not that meaningful and
and don't really fulfill us when you
when you then turn into this really
participatory community having all the
voices heard accessing collective
intelligence space you do get these
voices that are just basically repeating
the brainwashing of the old system
always have to use the frame like I'm
the sheep in wolf's clothing not the
other way around because I've I've had
to you know be in that corporate world
and and sell this stuff
um I think what I see is either the
Democratic Party of the Labour Party in
Australia the UK would happen us either
they take it they try it's all mostly
they try to solve everything in one
campaign platform it's print then what's
currently under the liberal regime that
scared the shit out of people even just
like me everyday we're talking to Saturn
hoon like how the fuck did the Liberal
Party get the working class behind them
Labour Party was for the working class
it's you have like truck drivers in
America voting for Trump but it was like
they're scared shitless a change so I
think there's there's got to be a new
approach to this and not so radical it's
got to be the journey you got to start
with the Acorn then let that movement
grow to an oak tree over time but you
got a they got a chin like the live the
Labour Party should have automatically
won the election here they just didn't
say fucking anything that happened would
have won but they went in and started
talking about all these tax changes and
all these radical changes which is scare
and everyday people that are stuck in a
system that was created by the Liberal
Party you know it's like they're nervous
about that changed I think there's got
to be a different way I mean my own my
whole strategy session today was like
how do we find the right Labour
candidate that really understands
feeding off don't think in a way to talk
about this stuff and frame it in a way
that brings them it unifies the party
it's a different way to talk about this
stuff and I I mean the UK's got so much
great momentum happening on cooperative
economy happening it looks like that the
local level and almost in a certain
point isn't really mattering what the
federal government's are doing because
the local the cities are making major
changes and local communities are
adopting some really great stuff so it's
it's that's a tough one man it's a
really tough one but it's it's the
narrative and how we sell it then it's
there we got to be as smart as
the wolf's are you know like is the
Republican regime or the Liberal Party
machine that's just fucking brilliant at
their tactics in those that those
tactics and we have to be you know smart
about how we do though one thing I
forgot though on the governance side is
tying it back to a a so like we also
have Carol Sanford running a CAD program
down there so people that have graduated
from TRP we have them in this ongoing
quarterly engagement there's 40 people
now on their New Zealand Australia
meeting up with Carol online this is
quarter down on the cat program specific
for people in there okay that with
Caroline Robertson each part of it and
then we're also doing what I'm doing
this learning journey for regenerative
practitioners it's kind of okay graduate
from TRP let's talk about the mental
model a bit more but let's bring in an
Aboriginal you know culture let's talk
about the integrated design process the
project management techniques for
delivering and executing on living
buildings that are you know the low-cost
it's this whole platform I've created
for the last ten years
we're looking at hosting the Regina says
training I have a called Pamela and Joel
next month with chels to do it on
country and actually start to bring
shells and other Aboriginal elders into
the teaching so there's knowledge
transfer between Eva Genesis and
Aboriginal Chileans so we can actually
look at a much more play space
understanding of regenerative elements
in your 80,000 years hmm
because that that was the the
conversation with Johnny Freelander that
that's I found so fascinating and in
October also seems to suggest that what
happened for him when he met Regenesis
and the the frameworks of regenerative
development was that he recognized that
he was a
a voicing of indigenous wisdom in
western language that age could build
the foundations of one side of the
bridge and and and and so he like he was
talking a lot about this framing I think
he'd just done a master's on this of
comparing square systems thinking of of
Western modernized people with the
circular systems thinking of indigenous
cultures and how how to bridge that yeah
can you close it for one second I just
have to go down there is something I
want to close out with you I think is
just running because otherwise I'll have
to file security
an interesting point to make in
correlation between regenerative
practitioner training and the 12th
program I'm in these training sessions
with Carol and Carol mentored me in
quite a while Al's and Seattle and every
time I it would always like come up in
conversation with her with Pamela our
bill Oh sounds like a a well that sounds
like kind of how I'm training in a I'm
not here like you said in a and I'm on
the calls with her or even during the
regenerative practitioner training that
I went through just to kind of see how
they taught it I would say that a lot
and then when I be able my breakout
sessions I'd be sharing you know
twelve-step experience up with the other
peers in the room and talk about how I
was trained
whatever Carol teaching is like oh I've
actually I came to that conclusion
through my sobriety nothing huh brought
it up to Carol again and she's like oh
yeah that because the same guy at
Harvard who created that framework
influenced bill to create 12-step to
influence early chrome that's based on
their general practitioner training idea
so the same guy at Harvard developed
that theory of change and framework that
influenced the creation of 12 steps was
the same person that the Charlie Brown
used that's influenced Pamela and Bill
and Ben on Vijender practice so from a
governance perspective I always like 12a
is really interesting as an NA there's
probably like three million people
worldwide it's not a huge amount people
but it's self governed there's leaders
it's very democratic around self funded
this exclusion of media like the rules
and traditions of the 12-step program
a really interesting to look at a
context of how we structure society
there's making but the principles the
steps are like destruction of the ego
not destruction but much to tempering
down of the ego and how I engage the
world everyday I guess it's a when I
talk about with what I'm teaching
regenerate or training it's like I every
day have to wake up and grab myself
right and I put my feet on the ground
and say I belong to the earth and I'm a
service to life but I learned how to do
that kind of stuff through hey when I
had to wake up and read literature call
my sponsor and set my like train my
brain to just start the way I need to
engage everyone around me that day or
life around them that day so I'm making
sure that I'm not self-seeking I'm
making sure I'm not making decisions on
my ego I'm making sure I'm being service
to people around me so it's the humidity
factor in that the mentality the mental
model I start my day with right and I
learned that in the 12-step program just
happened just by chance my journey as a
regenerative practitioner was so deeply
aligned with that but I had no idea you
know I know with how much it's helped me
as a practitioner and a change agent
because of my sobriety and learnings I
got from becoming sober and using 12
steps so this is really it's fascinating
because you know so much of the like the
framing of what's wrong with the
degenerative human presence on earth is
really you could say we're a heavily
addicted culture to patthamas
of using more and more to fill gaps that
you actually can't fill materially
because you need to fill it in meaning
and immaterial ebert with Reap
reconnecting to to nourishing
relationships to place and people and
and and I think oh advertising this
forces us to proceed how we should be
right it's like is create a conundrum so
in many ways too
EAL the the patterns of degeneration in
our globalized is isn't it
getting rid of an addiction and so the
so it kind of makes perfect sense that
similarity what's the what's the name of
the the guy who actually developed at
harvard you mentioned you know here
right well email sec no not very well
but yes you see me like wait wait
actually I haven't I've never talked to
Carol and personally yet we've had a
couple of emails exchanges so she does
it she's very candid to it's not like it
opened it's like this is the way you do
it kind of thing it's great she's great
mentor for London I everybody who have
talked to about her has had the
privilege of being somehow mentored by
her being in the cabs like the change
agent development groups that she set up
um deeply values what what they get out
of their conversations from from the
like I need to make that step of
actually having conversation with her
because I looking from from the outside
it is is that prickly kind of
maintaining the lineage and there's a
bit of an energy that I perceived
because I haven't really met her yet
that there is that reminds me of the old
martial art and if you have to empty
your glass so I can fill its type
approach of teaching and stories having
an interesting dialogue that with
regards to become an earth initial in
Santa Fe so we met with pennilyn Ben so
I think it can't just be the Regenesis
way you know it's almost become full
dish yeah that's that's that's the bit
that I feel that I know she's not doing
it out of ego trip but it has it has a
kind of culture atmosphere around it
like you inducted into this group and
they even the promise
I mean they're they're gardening how
it's hot and I'll I was kind of a
defender that when people start talking
about it down here or someone was being
slowing and talked about their
development I would email pendulum band
and be like you got those guys like no
they were I'm like weird you and I'm
good where do you where's your teacher
energy regeneration it's a go you know
I've been in the green building movement
on slit here you go through training
reeling they look like a couple times
I've had to step into a trade
organization and say no if you're going
to talk about this topic there's got to
be protocols and how its framed I was
talking about and it builds off the
people and I've been working in the
space for about 25 years
not so you know cowboy that just came
out in the last couple years and catch
on this new Trevor generation this is
what's happening everywhere around the
world now particularly in the business
world everybody wants a piece of
regeneration this and the other and and
the typical consultants that they jumped
on smart and then she jumped on circular
or whatever for while it was biomimicry
and just repackaged it it made it then
their current offering and now trying to
do exactly the same thing with
regeneration not understanding that
there is a depth of practice behind it
that is isn't as frustrated as I get
with that and I feel like I don't have a
book and nobody knows I have to write a
fucking book that's I know because I
just like I'm like how can I not be at
the table for that like I've been in
this for so long why anybody like I get
a lot of that I need to write a book but
but I'm also like backing away from
certain things because of this privilege
I had with working with chosen
Aboriginal didn't people here this is
right now I'm like the adolescent again
right and I'm getting all this knowledge
and seeing how his knowledge has led to
all these things that you I you know
seeing grow over the last 50 years and
then in a modest and other movement so I
think there's something deeper for us to
take home and I think a lot of dish you
did shell so you can so what we want to
was create with this online teaching
platform I don't know if it's oom or
whatever you might know some good place
to do it but just so and it's people can
come into it social net she'll create
her network of Aboriginal the First
Nations teachers in New Zealand and
Australia to link up and talk about
marine custodianship and how they look
at fisheries and how they look at food
production and botany and bush tucker
Gardens how we look at communal housing
and Malayan management techniques and
fire rate or whatever there might be so
there's all this teaching happening but
we have someone who's you know really
advanced in the field from Western
perspective also teaching with it she
sounds amazing as it as a service to
humanity almost building that program
the way I see it you know a systems in
traditionally glad your practice could
be the number one biggest export
Australia 80,000 years of applied
learning and how to live on this planet
in a regenerative manual it's just
basically every day I learned something
new and it helps me I've almost become
looking for reverse racism and it's like
look at white people we look at what
we've done we don't have it a lot of
stuff to justify our being sustained I
mean this is this is the deep question
that David asked me ten years ago raise
it like before we can answer what we
might have to do and how we might create
a sustainable human presence on earth we
have to ask a deeper question which is
why are we worth sustaining and I think
Aboriginal cultures have a lot more to
answer like reasons why are they worth
sustaining then in our Western cultural
track record and that kind of
degenerative exploitative species
behavior isn't worth sustaining we
really need to reinvent ourselves
there's a training
had to go through training on this was a
book called decolonizing solidarity so
it helps train understand non-indigenous
people on how to be in service to
dealing with indigenous causes and
movements and that's helped me develop
this level of respect and rapport with
Aboriginal Australians that most whilst
remnants can't get either there's just
like burdening guilt that contemporary
Australians have about the past that
don't maybe they don't engage it there's
also a deep lack of awareness about
their own history what happens here and
and the value of Aboriginal culture to
our society or it's to kissably applied
through art in place making strategies
or any place in learning so it's missing
this much deeper value impact it has and
so we're just going on that journey man
and be awesome
I'll definitely set up a car with you
and Jill so you guys do know gift so I
probably have to wrap it up we've been
talking book almost an hour and a half
but it's been so nice to reconnect
particularly we didn't have enough time
in London m2 and hopefully this is the
first of the number of ways of us to you
and I can collectively bring back to you
come here so I've been talking to Freya
and Rolla about this stuff and inviting
shells and it wasn't lost on me in that
room that a lot of that wisdom First
Nations people
I was the highlight of of the event was
was particularly the New Zealand
delegation and I know a strategy with
New Zealand government with them so we
have a call and January let's remove it
which is good great
so I just